Okay, so let's talk about
another very important
project artifact called the
Work Breakdown Structure.
Now, the WBS, or the Work Breakdown
Structure, is basically a graphical
hierarchy of all the work that needs to be
done, right?
It's just basically showing just a
breakdown of all of the work, okay?
Now, let me just show you first a very
simple example of what a work breakdown
structure looks like, right, before we go
through all of these points here.
So my next slide, he is a
very simple example then
of a WBS, right, or a
work breakdown structure.
A very simple example, right?
So we have a simple project here,
a kitchen remodeling project.
So what's involved in this kitchen
remodeling project?
Well, we need some appliances,
we need countertops, right?
We need to build some cabinets.
We need to install some flooring.
And then we're going to further break this
down, you know, appliances.
We can keep some old appliances.
we need some new appliances, right,
with countertops, right, some new
countertops, maybe you could keep some old
countertops.
It's cabinets as well, some new cabinets,
some old cabinets, and with flooring,
right, with flooring, well, we have to
have new flooring.
And then we further break this down.
Old appliances, well, maybe the only old
appliances that's worth keeping is a
microwave, right, but we need some new
appliances, we need a refrigerator,
the oven and the dishwasher, right?
And then with the flooring, right,
need, foyer flooring, kitchen flooring,
and then maybe also we'd break down
countertops and cabinets as well.
But we're just showing the appliances and
flooring here.
So at a glance, we can
look at this and have a good
understanding of all the
work that needs to be done.
And that's really what a work breakdown
structure is.
We're breaking down this project.
We're breaking it down into basically
smaller pieces.
Think a progressive elaboration.
I mean, this is a perfect example of
progressive elaboration.
Starting off with something
high level and then
gradually breaking it down
into more and more details.
And in fact, if I go
to the previous slide,
notice the heading
here says decomposition.
Decomposition is the
tool and technique, if you
like, of creating the
work breakdown structure.
That's what you're utilizing.
You're utilizing a tool and technique
called decomposition, right?
Which is breaking down the project to more
manageable units of
work that can be estimated.
Each unit of work here now, we can
estimate.
So basically, if you have to summarize
this process, the summary of this process
is decomposing your
project down to the lowest
level, which is known as a work package.
So I'll talk about that in just a second.
But decomposition is a tool technique
here.
Now, let me just quickly go to the to the
next slide now because there's a few
important terms you need to know regarding
the work breakdown structure so first of
all the lowest level of the work breakdown
structure is known as a work package right
the lowest level is known as a work
package they're breaking all this down so
in this case if you're looking at the
flooring the foyer flooring kitchen
flooring this would be known as a work
package okay so if i go back to the full
work breakdown structure all of these ones
down here, like the last level,
this would be known as the work package.
Now, the importance of the
work package is, when you further
break down a work package,
you get individual activities.
The other important part to know,
though, for the purpose of PMI standards
and the PMP exam, the WBS does not include
activities.
That's a completely separate process.
I will talk about that in a separate
video.
But here, what we're talking about is the
WBS.
The work breakdown structure only goes as
far as a work package.
So if they ever ask you on
the exam, and they might do,
what is the lowest level of
the work breakdown structure?
Lowest level is the work package.
It's just that when you
further break down a
work package, you
get individual activities.
Now, a level above a work package is known
as a control account.
And the importance of
the control account is this
is where you do your
mathematical computations.
So this is where you measure the health of
your project, if you like.
You measure the performance of your
project.
So all of these earned value calculations
that we are talking about in a separate
video, in the budgeting section,
the cost section.
All of those formulas are we head or
schedule, behind schedule, over budget,
under budget.
They are all set at the control account
level.
And the whole principle behind this is,
if a work package is behind schedule,
for example, foyer flooring, if
that's behind schedule, does
that mean the entire project is
going to be behind schedule?
Not necessarily.
But if this control account is behind
schedule, like the entire new flooring is
behind schedule, then yes, that might put
the whole project behind schedule.
So you can set your control account at any
layer of the work breakdown structure,
any level, But generally, it is set one
level above the work package.
I mean, the default is one level above the
work package for the example.
You'll also come across this term here,
code of account.
Code of account is basically this unique
numbering system.
So if I go back to the previous slide,
the work breakdown structure here,
this numbering system here, the 1.1,
1.1.2, 1.1.2.
2.1, et cetera, et cetera.
This unique numbering system is known as a
code of account.
Now, you can use any combination of
alphi-numeric characters, right?
But the whole principle or the whole
reason for having a code of account is
basically to show all these work breakdown
structure items, how they're rolling up
each layer of the work breakdown
structure, right?
How are they, you know, flowing up the
work breakdown structure?
It's easy to see when you have this code
of account.
Now, when you only have a one-page work
breakdown structure like this,
I mean, it's easy to see anyway.
But what if you have a hundred-page work
breakdown structure?
Not so easy to follow then.
So that's why, you know,
if you have these code of
accounts there, it's easy
to follow up now, right?
Where does one work breakdown structure
item?
Where does it lead to?
What is it related to?
And so and so forth.
And then another term I want to mention is
this one called the planning package.
And a planning package really is nothing
more than a placeholder.
It's just basically, you know,
once we have all the details, this
planning package will become a work
package.
That's really all it is.
We don't have any details yet.
We know there's something that needs to be
done here.
We don't have all the details.
So once we get the detail, that planning
package becomes a work package.
Now, if I go back to the first slide,
a couple of things I want to mention.
First of all, why do we have this work
breakdown structure?
Well, as I said, it's a graphical
hierarchy, shows all the words.
that needs to be done, right?
It's easy to understand, right?
If I show you the work breakdown structure
again, it's very easy to understand.
Anybody can look at this and
have a good understanding
or at this is all the work
that needs to be done.
And plus, it can help you identify in any
work that's missing.
Like for example, we're doing a kitchen
remodeling, we need appliances,
countertops, cabinets, flooring,
do we need to rewire the kitchen?
All of a sudden now, you might have
realized we've missed something here, right?
So, it's It's basically, it identifies,
you know, can identify any missed work,
right?
It's making sure that work doesn't get
missed.
Plus, because it's easy to understand,
allows for team buying, allows the team
members to understand how their work fits
in with the overall picture, right,
the overall project, right, serves as a
communication tool because
it's easy to understand.
It's also, therefore, you know,
it can be used to do an impact analysis
for any changes, can evaluate any scope
changes, right?
If we make a change
here, what are the areas
of the project is this going to impact?
And of course, this is a kitchen
remodeling.
I mean, just think of a much, much larger
project.
One change in one area
of the project can lead
to a change in another
area of the project.
And this actually becomes a foundation for
planning because now we can break each of
these work breakdown structure items, the
work package, and individual activities.
Now, this is for a predictive project.
in an agile environment, the decomposition
in an agile works slightly differently,
very slightly.
Remember, in an agile, requirements are
known as user stories.
And just like any requirement,
you have a high level requirement and then
you're breaking it down into more detail
requirements.
So user story is a detail requirement,
right?
And it has, you know,
some kind of functionality
that will provide value to the customer.
And it meets this criteria
called Invest, which
we will cover in detail
in a separate video.
But in an agile environment, a large user
story, right, you get a
high-level user story.
A large user story is known as an epic.
Then you further break it
down into features, which are
basically features are
going to include capabilities.
So several features then will make up an
epic.
And then these features are broken down
into user stories.
And several user stories make up a
feature.
Now, these user Stories, remember,
are requirements.
In order to actually fulfill those
requirements, you need to create activities.
And so these user stories then are broken
down into several tasks.
And you have to have
several tasks, several
activities, basically
to fulfill a user story.
Okay, so this is a basic decomposition in
an Agile environment.